Register of the Mikhail Mikhailovich Krasil'nikov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mikhail Mikhailovich Krasil'nikov papers
1948-1996
2000C29
Krasil'nikov, Mikhail Mikhailovich, 1933-1996.
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Krasil'nikov papers are comprised of poems, correspondence, legal documents, printed matter, and photographs relating to political dissent in the Soviet Union, conditions in forced labor camps, Russian literature, and Russian-Latvian cultural relations.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1933 Born, Orsha, Belarus (Soviet Union)
1948 Moved with family to Riga
1951 Entered Leningrad State University
1956 Arrested and convicted for anti-Soviet activities after participating in a Leningrad demonstration
1957-1960 Prisoner, gulag camp in Mordoviia
1960 Released from camp. Returned to Riga, Latvia
1960-1996 Worked as a tour guide and writer in Riga, Latvia
1996 Died, Riga, Latvia
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers document the life of the poet from his university days to his death in 1996. Much of the collection relates to Krasil'nikov's arrest for anti-Soviet political activities and his imprisonment in the gulag from 1957 to 1960. Arrest records, notebooks, photographs and correspondence cover this period of Krasil'nikov's life and are included in the Personal File.
The Correspondence File consists of personal letters received by Krasil'nikov. During his time in the gulag, Krasil'nikov corresponded with family and other writers from his circle, such as Mikhail Eremin, Vladimir Ufliand and Leonid Vinogradov.
The bulk of the collection, which is included in the Writings and Writings by Others series, consists of poetry from the 1950s-1970s by Krasil'nikov and other authors, particularly Aleksandr Mikhailovich Kondratov and Vladimir Ufliand. The Writings by Others series also includes samizdat and newspaper articles on Russian and Soviet literature collected by Krasil'nikov.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Civil rights -- Soviet Union.; Russian literature.; Dissenters -- Soviet Union.; Political prisoners -- Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation) -- Civilization; Latvia -- Civilization
Collection Contents
- Personal File, 1948-1996 (Box 1)
  Includes identification documents, school and medical evaluations, photographs of Krasil'nikov and members of his circle, arrest records and notebooks from his imprisonment in the gulag. A career file also includes tourism articles written by the author as well as concert and exhibition programs.
  - Education records, 1948-1961 (Folder 1:1)
  - Identification documents, 1951-1969 (Folder 1:2)
  - Notebooks, 1951-1960 (Folder 1:3-4)
    Includes notebooks kept during his imprisonment
  - Photographs, 1951-1996 (Folder 1:5)
  - Medical and work records, 1953-1987 (Folder 1:6)
  - Arrest and imprisonment file, 1957-1960 (Folder 1:7)
    Includes search warrants, correspondence with the prosecutor and release records
  - Clippings, 1957 (Folder 1:8)
    Contains articles from camp newspaper, Za otlichnyi trud
  - Tour guide career file, circa 1960s-1980s (Folder 1:9)
    Includes tourism articles written by Krasil'nikov
  - Programs, circa 1960s-1980s (Folder 1:10)
    Includes concert and exhibition programs in Riga and elsewhere
- Correspondence, 1957-1979 (Box 1-2)
  Contains letters of a personal nature, primarily those received by Krasil'nikov while in prison. Arranged alphabetically by name of the correspondent.
  - Bakinskii, Vadim, 1957 (Folder 1:11)
  - Eremin, Mikhail, 1958 (Folder 1:11)
  - Gerasimov, Vladimir, 1958 (Folder 1:11)
  - Grishchenko, B., 1958 (Folder 1:11)
  - Katerinich, Valentina, 1957-1960 (Folder 1:12)
  - Kitaenko, Aleksandr, 1957 (Folder 1:13)
  - Kravchenko, V., 1957 (Folder 1:13)
  - Krasil'nikov family, 1957-1960 (Folder 1:13)
  - Krivoshein, Igor Aleksandrovich, 1961-1965 (Folder 1:13)
  - Kuple, Sergei and Natal?ia, 1958 (Folder 1:13)
  - Lauva, Karl, 1957-1958 (Folder 1:14)
  - Losev, Lev (Lev Lifshits), 1957 (Folder 1:14)
  - Mikhailov, Iurii and Alla, 1957 (Folder 1:14)
  - Panteleev, 1964 (Folder 1:14)
  - Polovnikov, Boris Grigor'evich, 1957 (Folder 1:14)
  - Riabinina, Kira, 1957-1961 (Folder 2:1)
  - Rozengauz, B., 1954 (Folder 2:2)
  - Semenov, V., 1957 (Folder 2:2)
  - Sharymov, A., 1957 (Folder 2:2)
  - Tselkov, Oleg, 1957-1960 (Folder 2:2)
  - Tsimbal, Irina, 1957-1958 (Folder 2:2)
  - Ufliand, Vladimir, circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 2:3)
  - Vinogradov, Leonid and Natal'ia, 1957-1958 (Folder 2:3)
  - Unattributed, 1958-1979 (Folder 2:4)
    Arranged by year
- Writings, 1957-1963 (Box 2)
  Consists of poems written by Krasil'nikov. Arranged chronologically.
  - Poems, 1957-1963 (Folder 2: 5)
- Writings by Others, 1952-1981 (Box 2-3)
  Contains manuscripts and typescripts by other authors in Krasil'nikov's circle. The bulk of the series consists of poems by Aleksandr Mikhailovich Kondratov. This series also includes samizdat materials and newspaper articles on Russian literature clipped by Krasil'nikov. Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Chertkov, L., Nerastankino, typescript, 1958-1962 (Folder 2:6)
  - Eremin, Mikhail, [poems], typescript, undated (Folder 2:6)
  - Goliavkin, A., short stories, undated (Folder 2:6)
    - Gvozd' v stole (Folder 2:6)
    - On govorit' - ia govoriu (Folder 2:6)
    - Privet vam ptitsy (Folder 2:6)
  - Kondratov, Aleksandr Mikhailovich, poems, 1952-1981 (Folder 2-3:)
    - Chasti rechi, undated (Folder 2:7)
    - Gor'kie maksimki, undated (Folder 2:7)
    - I t.d., transcript, 1959-1976 (Folder 2:7)
    - Kashchei: roman v stikhakh, 1975 (Folder 2:8)
    - Komy na Rusi zhit' khorosho?, undated (Folder 2:8)
    - Liricheskii dnevnik, 1952-1967 (Folder 2:9)
    - Ob etom bestiarii, undated (Folder 2:9)
    - Rasput'ki, 1980-1981 (Folder 3:1)
    - Skirli, undated (Folder 3:2)
    - Stikhi tekh let, typescript, undated (Folder 3:3)
    - Tam za stenoi, typescript, 1952-1958 (Folder 3:4)
    - Tri matreshki, undated (Folder 3:5)
    - Miscellaneous poems, undated (Folder 3:5)
    - School notebook, 1956 February 20 - 1956 June 6 (Folder 3:5)
    - Chto zhe takoe ioga? Nauka i religiia article, 1975 (Folder 3:5)
  - Kuple, Sergei, poems, undated (Folder 3:6)
  - Lesopravskii, Iurii, Sosny rastut v zone, circa 1965 (Folder 3:7)
  - Mikhailov, Iurii, Notebook, circa 1950s-1960s (Folder 3:8)
  - Semenov, V., undated (Folder 3:9)
  - Ufliand, Vladimir, undated (Folder 3:9)
  - Unattributed miscellaneous poems, undated (Folder 3:9)
  - Samizdat, undated (Folder 3:10)
    Includes typescripts of Joseph Brodsky, Viacheslav Ivanov, Osip Mandel'shtam, Boris Pasternak, Marina Tsvetaeva, and Nikolai Zabolotskii
  - Clippings on Russian literature, 1950s-1980s and undated (Folder 3:11)
    Includes articles on Russian literature